<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Compassionate Path</title>
    <description></description>
    <link>/</link>
    <atom:link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <pubDate>Tue, 07 Jun 2016 12:11:24 -0400</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 07 Jun 2016 12:11:24 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.0.2</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Cajon and Practice - Part 1</title>
        <description>&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/-uLsM9vp3dw&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For my birthday my wife bought me a cajon (a wooden box drum). (Set aside for a moment your cognitive dissonance of the thought of a 64 yr. old Zen Buddhist Monk playing something as cool as a cajon.) Here is my current plan on learning to play.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;the-plan&quot;&gt;The Plan&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;marginnote&quot;&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;fullwidth&quot; src=&quot;/img/cajon2.png&quot; /&gt; &lt;/span&gt;
I am not even going to open the box until I can play the cajon. Here’s the plan. Every Sunday I am going to watch YouTube cajon videos (like the one above and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=aIzckuLjwik&quot;&gt;this one&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=lQ1qxn47GxM&quot;&gt;this one&lt;/a&gt;). So I will do that for at least 2 hours every Sunday. And I bought a bunch of books from Amazon about playing the cajon. Here is an excerpt from one:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;There is no question about this relationship of the top arm to the level where tone is produced. If the fingers, hand, or forearm have any bearing down on their own initiative, the tone simply does not come off. They each become an integrated unit with the top arm control; they make the top arm effective in contacting tone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am not entirely sure what that means but it sounds important. So I will memorize it. I am going to dedicate 1 hour a day to reading these books and memorizing the material in them. So that is my plan. It is the start of June now and if I do this to mid-August that will be about 100 hours devoted to learning to play the cajon. Then I will take the cajon out of the box, unwrap it, sit down and play the cajon flawlessly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;hows-that-for-a-plan&quot;&gt;How’s that for a plan?&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maybe you are thinking that I won’t successfully play the cajon and I bet it is that you think I am not spending enough time on my new hobby. So here is my new plan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;the-revised-plan&quot;&gt;The Revised Plan&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Basically it is the same as the first except I will spend 20 hours per week watching YouTube videos and reading books and I will not open the box until Christmas. That is 1,000 hours devoted to learning to play the cajon–10 times more than the previous  plan. Won’t it be a lovely gift to my wife to wake up on Christmas morning to some virtuosic cajon beats.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think everyone can see that this plan is totally misguided. What is missing is practice, and plenty of it. If I did deliberative practice for those 20 hours per week instead of reading and watching YouTube videos, I probably could lay down some dope beats by Christmas. In the musical realm it is quite obvious to all of us that practice is the key.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But what about our spiritual life? &lt;span class=&quot;marginnote&quot;&gt;This blog post is nearly identical to a talk I gave years ago about this topic. Here is the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=0dD7Sbz9ayc&quot;&gt;YouTube link&lt;/a&gt;.  &lt;/span&gt;What people view as a foolhearty plan related to the cajon, they may view as valid when related to a spiritual path. Going to Sunday service, watching inspirational YouTube videos, reading books. That sounds good. But if that is the extent of it, it is as misguided as my cajon plan. What is missing is practice and plenty of it. You may think &lt;em&gt;I DO practice&lt;/em&gt;. I read something in a book and apply it to my everyday life. That may work for some things, but I think it is equivalent to me buying a cajon and immediately joining Santana. I will read books at night and apply what I learn to me playing on stage with Santana. But clearly, a Santana stage performance is too complex to just jump into and apply what I learned watching YouTube videos. All the band members of Santana have spent years learning to play their instruments. And the band itself practices for hours. Hiromi, a phenomenal jazz pianist says this about her band:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It requires a lot of rehearsal to play the songs. My band always tells me I better change the group’s name from Sonicbloom to Boot Camp!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similary, life is too complex and chaotic to immediately transfer what you learn in books to everyday situations. For example, you have probably read multiple times about mindfulness, but chances are, in the middle of your work day you may not be mindful. Racing around, traffic, kids, the 101 things you need to do. You are not focused on the suggestions from a book–you are just trying to survive in the modern world. Deliberative practice enables us to work with what we learn from books so that it naturally arises without effort in everyday situations. All of a sudden, without thinking, without effort, we have moments of mindfulness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hiromi says “Focus, continuous training, and love and passion for what you do, more you practice, more you can fly” and “I wanted to bring what Jackie Chan does in Kung Fu to what I do on piano.” The more you meditate, do compassion training, and other practices the more you can fly in everyday life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my next post I will dive into this a bit more.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 06 Jun 2016 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>/posts/2016/06/cajon.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/posts/2016/06/cajon.html</guid>
        
        <category>practice</category>
        
        
        <category>jekyll</category>
        
        <category>rstats</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Don&#39;t Know</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/img/seungsahn.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;fullwidth&quot; src=&quot;/img/seungsahn.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;marginnote&quot;&gt;Zen Master Seung Sahn. Art from the website &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.prajna-galleries.com/&quot;&gt;prajna-galleries&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As many of you know we have been searching for a space to hold our meditation sessions and other events. We sent out a number of emails to area churches and looked at commercial office space to rent. A few times it looked like we found what we were looking for, only to discover some wrinkle that made the space either far less than ideal or unavailable. Last night I heard of the possibility of a fantastic space–better than any we have looked at so far. So the possibility of having a great meditation space may be on the horizon–or maybe not. This morning, while walking my dogs, I realized that this process of looking for a space is similar to the famous Chinese farmer story. For those unfamiliar with it it goes something like this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once upon a time there was a Chinese farmer who lost a horse–it ran away. And his neighbors came around that evening and said “That’s too bad! That is most unfortunate!” And he said “maybe.” The next day the horse came back and brought seven wild horses with him. And his neighbors came around that evening and said “Why that is fantastic, isn’t it?” And he said “maybe.” The next day his son was trying to train the wild horses and broke his leg while attempted to ride one. And, of course, the neighbors came around and said “That is awful! That’s too bad!” And the farmer said “maybe.” The following day army officers came around the village conscripting all young men into the military. They rejected the son because of this broken leg. Yet again, the neighbors came around and this time they said “Fantastic news, you must be very happy.” And the farmer said “maybe.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So is it good news that we found a potentially wonderful meditation space? 
Maybe&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alan Watts said of the Chinese farmer story:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The &lt;span class=&quot;marginnote&quot;&gt;This is from his book &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/Eastern-Wisdom-Modern-Life-Collected/dp/1577311809/?tag=braipick-20&quot;&gt;Eastern Wisdom, Modern Life: Collected Talks 1960-1969&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.worldcat.org/title/eastern-wisdom-modern-life-collected-talks-1960-1969/oclc/68373273&amp;amp;referer=brief_results&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;public library&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;whole process of nature is an integrated process of immense complexity, and it’s really impossible to tell whether anything that happens in it is good or bad—because you never know what will be the consequence of the misfortune; or, you never know what will be the consequences of good fortune.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am at a truck stop in west Texas. Someone approaches me as I pump gas, tells me he has no money but he needs to get to Arkansas to stay with his brother. I give him $10. Will the consequences of that act be good or bad? I simply don’t know. Maybe good; maybe bad. We can extend this don’t know mind to everything.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stephen Batchelor writes &lt;span class=&quot;marginnote&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/Confession-Buddhist-Atheist-Stephen-Batchelor/dp/0385527071/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1456706662&amp;amp;sr=8-1&amp;amp;keywords=confessions+of+a+buddhist+atheist&quot;&gt;Confession of a Buddhist Atheist&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.worldcat.org/title/confession-of-a-buddhist-atheist/oclc/401141622&amp;amp;referer=brief_results&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;public library&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;of his time in a Zen Monastery in South Korea:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;All I do, hour after hour, is ask myself the question &lt;em&gt;What is this?&lt;/em&gt; … All I did for ten hours a day for the next three months was ask myself this question. The first two weeks, when my back hurt and my mind swung between febrile daydreams&lt;span class=&quot;marginnote&quot;&gt;febrile daydreams = fever-like daydreams&lt;/span&gt; and lethargy, and the last few days, when I strove unsuccessfully not to look forward to the retreat ending, were the hardest. Throughout the long middle period, I experienced an unprecedented contentment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The point of this exercise, common in Zen, is to&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;short-circuit the brain’s answer-giving habit and leave you in a state of serene puzzlement. This doubt, or “perplexity” as I preferred to call it, then slowly starts to infuse one’s consciousness as a whole. Rather than struggling with the words of the question, one settles into a mood of quiet focused astonishment, in which one one simply waits and listens in the pregnant silence that follows the fading of words&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Zen Master Seung Sahn wrote in a letter&lt;span class=&quot;marginnote&quot;&gt;This is from his wonderful book &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/Dropping-Ashes-Buddha-Teachings-Master/dp/0802130526/ref=sr_1_2?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1456703920&amp;amp;sr=8-2&amp;amp;keywords=seung+sahn&quot;&gt;Dropping Ashes on the Buddha: The Teachings of Zen Master Seung Sahn&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.worldcat.org/title/dropping-ashes-on-the-buddha-the-teaching-of-zen-master-seung-sahn/oclc/2542074&amp;amp;referer=brief_results&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;public library&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;You must keep don’t know mind always and everywhere. This is the true practice of Zen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The Great Way is not difficult
&lt;br /&gt;if you don’t make distinctions.
&lt;br /&gt;Only throw away likes and dislikes
 &lt;br /&gt;and everything will be perfectly clear.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;So throw away all opinions, all likes and dislikes, and only keep the mind that doesn’t know. This is very important. Don’t know mind is the mind that cuts off all thinking. When all thinking has been cut off, you become empty mind. This is before thinking. Your before thinking mind, my before thinking mind, all people’s before thinking minds are the same. This is your substance. Your substance, my substance, and the substance of the whole universe become one. So the tree, the mountain, the cloud and you become one. Then I ask you: Are the mountain and you the same or different?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The mind that becomes one with the universe is before thinking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 25 Feb 2016 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>/posts/2016/02/maybe.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/posts/2016/02/maybe.html</guid>
        
        <category>loneliness</category>
        
        
        <category>jekyll</category>
        
        <category>rstats</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Valentine&#39;s Day and the opposite of loneliness</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/img/keegan.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;fullwidth&quot; src=&quot;/img/keegan.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;marginnote&quot;&gt;Marina Keegan. Photo from the book &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/Opposite-Loneliness-Essays-Stories/dp/1476753911/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1455501362&amp;amp;sr=8-1&amp;amp;keywords=the+opposite+of+loneliness&quot;&gt;The Opposite of Loneliness: Essays and Stories&lt;/a&gt; by Marina Keegan. Ms. Keegan died in a car crash just five days after graduating magna cum laude from Yale.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Marina Keegan–a 22 year old–wrote this a few weeks before her college commencement at Yale:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We don’t have a word for the opposite of loneliness, but if we &lt;span class=&quot;marginnote&quot;&gt;See &lt;a href=&quot;http://yaledailynews.com/blog/2012/05/27/keegan-the-opposite-of-loneliness/&quot;&gt;the complete Opposite of Loneliness essay&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;did, I could say that’s what I want in life. What I’m grateful and thankful to have found at Yale, and what I’m scared of losing when we wake up tomorrow and leave this place.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It’s not quite love and it’s not quite community; it’s just this feeling that there are people, an abundance of people, who are in this together. Who are on your team. When the check is paid and you stay at the table. When it’s four a.m. and no one goes to bed. That night with the guitar. That night we can’t remember. That time we did, we went, we saw, we laughed, we felt. The hats.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We all, I think, have had similar experiences to hers. The camaraderie of a college experience, of  being in the military, of a close-knit group in high school. The feeling that there are people that are in this together. Those are very intense experiences. Imagine what life would be like if we experienced that, every moment of our day. With everyone we meet or see we would have this intense feeling that we are in this together, we are on the same team, with everyone. even people who cut us off in traffic or have an opposing political view.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We would still have sufferings in our life. We might lose our job, have difficulties in a relationship, have sickness, maybe even chronic illness. But we would feel 100% supported and feel that the entire community has our back.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, many of us don’t feel this strong sense of community. Rather we feel loneliness and a sense of separation. Mother Teresa reportedly said: &lt;em&gt;The biggest disease today is not leprosy or tuberculosis but rather the feeling of not belonging&lt;/em&gt; 
Modern society with its emphasis on individualism seems to exasperate this problem by emphasizing the self. In contrast, in Buddhism we work at letting the self fall away and reducing the barriers between ourselves and the rest of the world.  Buddhism strives for the opposite of loneliness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The book we will start discussing next week, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/Radical-Acceptance-Embracing-Heart-Buddha/dp/0553380990/ref=sr_1_1?s=books&amp;amp;ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1455190721&amp;amp;sr=1-1&amp;amp;keywords=radical+acceptance&quot;&gt;Radical Acceptance: Embracing Your Life With the Heart of a Buddha&lt;/a&gt; by Tara Brach, presents methods that help us on this path. Please consider joining us for this book study.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 14 Feb 2016 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>/posts/2016/02/loneliness.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/posts/2016/02/loneliness.html</guid>
        
        <category>loneliness</category>
        
        
        <category>jekyll</category>
        
        <category>rstats</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Thanksgiving &amp; Gratitude</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/img/oliver_motorcycle2.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;fullwidth&quot; src=&quot;/img/oliver_motorcycle2.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;marginnote&quot;&gt;Dr Oliver Sacks. Photo from the book &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/Move-Life-Oliver-Sacks/dp/0385352549/ref=tmm_hrd_swatch_0?_encoding=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1448736664&amp;amp;sr=8-1-fkmr0&quot;&gt;On the Move: A Life&lt;/a&gt; by Oliver Sacks.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope everyone has had a wonderful Thanksgiving. As usual Cheryl and I spent our Thanksgiving with my ex-sister-in-law (long story) and her family. Eleven of us around a makeshift table talking, telling stories, laughing. It was fun and relaxing. On the day after Thanksgiving I reflected on giving thanks. There were periods in my life when I did daily gratitude practice. About ten years ago, I would do a chant-like gratitude practice while running. Then there was a period when I would write gratitudes in a journal. More recently, when I would go outside for the first time in the morning, I would look at the sky and give thanks for the new day. For some reason those practices faded.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I thought my life benefited from those practices. A belief supported by research. In a &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.breakthroughealing.org/Documents/GratitudeStudy2003.pdf&quot;&gt;seminal study&lt;/a&gt; published in 2003, Dr. Robert A. Emmons and Dr. Michael E. McCullough divided 200 undergraduates into three groups. One group wrote weekly ‘gratitude’ reports. The instructions were:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;There are many things in our lives, both large and small, that we might
be grateful about. Think back over the past week and write down on
the lines below up to five things in your life that you are grateful or
thankful for.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Members of one of the other group wrote weekly reports about hassles in their lives (&lt;em&gt;stupid people driving,&lt;/em&gt; and
&lt;em&gt;doing a favor for friend who didn’t appreciate it&lt;/em&gt; ) and members of the final group were asked to write about events in their lives (&lt;em&gt;cleaned out my shoe closet&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;talked to a doctor about medical school&lt;/em&gt; ). After ten weeks the researchers discovered that compared to the other two groups, the gratitude group felt more positive about their lives, exercised more, and were healthier. That is quite an amazing return on just spending a few minutes a week writing down what you are grateful for!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Often our lives are focused on desires. Desires for something we want like some shiny new gizmo for Christmas (I can spend hours and hours researching shiny gizmos on the web). Desires to have something end that we don’t like–like this sprained ankle I seem to have or the world to be less violent. We spend our days focusing on desires. Thinking about the future. Gratitude practice is a good antedote for desires. It helps us focus on the present. It helps us see things clearly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve previously mentioned Maria Popova and her excellent blog &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.brainpickings.org/&quot;&gt;brainpickings&lt;/a&gt;. In a review she wrote of the book &lt;em&gt;thxthxthx&lt;/em&gt; she writes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We live in a culture with far, far too much pessimism, cynicism and dystopianism going around. It’s easy to dismiss any inkling of positivity as self-serving Pollyannism, yet there’s plenty of evidence that recognizing our simple blessings greatly increases our well-being. I’m certainly a believer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The book, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/exec/obidos/ASIN/1449402941/&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;thxthxthx&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, by the way, consists of 200 handwritten thank you notes by Leah Dieterich including:
&lt;a href=&quot;/img/thxthxthx1.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;fullwidth&quot; src=&quot;/img/thxthxthx1.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;/img/thx_122.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;fullwidth&quot; src=&quot;/img/thx_122.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps it is time, as Maria Popova suggests, to recognize ‘our simple blessings’. To acknowledge and be grateful for what we have. To be grateful for the life we do have–the good and the bad. Be grateful for, as buddhists say, the 10,000 joys and the 10,000 sorrows of life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oliver Sacks, in his book &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/Gratitude-Oliver-Sacks/dp/0451492935/ref=asap_bc?ie=UTF8&quot;&gt;Gratitude&lt;/a&gt; writes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;At nearly 80, with a scattering of medical and surgical problems, none disabling, I feel glad to be alive — “I’m glad I’m not dead!” sometimes bursts out of me when the weather is perfect… I am grateful that I have experienced many things — some wonderful, some horrible — and that I have been able to write a dozen books, to receive innumerable letters from friends, colleagues and readers, and to enjoy what Nathaniel Hawthorne called “an intercourse with the world.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 28 Nov 2015 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>/posts/2015/11/thanksgiving.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/posts/2015/11/thanksgiving.html</guid>
        
        <category>gratitude</category>
        
        
        <category>jekyll</category>
        
        <category>rstats</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>A Discussion on Compassion.</title>
        <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Compassion is the ability to see what needs doing right now and the willingness to do it right now&lt;/em&gt; - Brad Warner, Zen Priest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;It is not enough to espouse compassion, you have to act on it to make it real&lt;/em&gt; - Dalai Lama.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The whole idea of compassion is based on a keen awareness of the interdependence of all these living beings, which are all part of one another, and all involved in one another&lt;/em&gt; - Thomas Merton&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We all live busy lives. We work at hard jobs often putting in more than 40 hours per week. Then there are all the other tasks that need doing: laundry, shopping, cooking, taking care of our kids or our parents. We unwind by watching a tv show or by surfing the web. Sometimes it seems that if we can live this modern life and just have a bit of happiness, that would be enough. We may be aware of compassion but don’t take time to consciously fit compassionate acts into our lives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just this past week I received email from a friend–a Zen priest who was ordained at the same ceremony I was. He said he was quitting his university job in Oregon and moving to Maryland with his wife and kids to live and work in a Catholic Worker intentional community that serves the homeless. That seems like a life focused on helping others. But what about the rest of us who are struggling with living, not in a monastic intentional community, but in modern urban life? Where does compassion and helping others fit in?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would like to invite you to a discussion on Sunday 15 November at 2pm at Blackstone Coffee, 1113 Jefferson Davis Hwy (look for a ‘Zen’ sign on our table). The topics are 1) how can we be more compassionate in our daily lives and 2) what can we do as a small community to foster compassion. To seed this discussion, I have a few short videos and a few web links.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This first video (surprisingly, an insurance company advertisement) was discovered by Ted Pickett, one of our community members.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/8OMGsVnqvyA&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This next one is in a similar vein:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/NugINWYhHRA&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This last video is from an organization envisioned by the Dalai Lama called &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.joinaforce4good.org/&quot;&gt;A Force For Good&lt;/a&gt; (There is a variety of information on &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.joinaforce4good.org/&quot;&gt;their website&lt;/a&gt; and a short explanation at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.6seconds.org/2015/09/15/daniel-goleman-on-the-dalai-lamas-vision-for-good/&quot;&gt;Daniel Goleman on the Dalai Lama’s Vision for Good&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bernie Glassman (&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tetsugen_Bernard_Glassman&quot;&gt;wikipedia article&lt;/a&gt;) authored a number of books about engaged buddhism. He offers three tenets:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt; Entering the stream of Socially Engaged Spirituality, I vow to live a life of:
 Not-knowing, thereby giving up fixed ideas about ourselves and the universe
 Bearing witness to the joy and suffering of the world
 Doing Action arising from Not Knowing and Bearing Witness
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are some interesting short articles &lt;a href=&quot;http://zenpeacemakers.org/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, including &lt;a href=&quot;http://zenpeacemakers.org/zen-peacemakers/who-we-are/zen-peacemakers-sangha/dharma-talks/bernie-day-with-bernie/&quot;&gt;A Day with Bernie Glassman&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://zenpeacemakers.org/zen-peacemakers/who-we-are/zen-peacemakers-sangha/dharma-talks/bernie-divinity-lecture-3/&quot;&gt;Bearing Witness- A Harvard Divinity School Talk&lt;/a&gt; (this last talk mentions a video about him which I could not find on the web).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have other videos or links you think relevant to the discussion please post them to &lt;a href=&quot;http://compassionatepath.org/forum.html&quot;&gt;our forum&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope to see you at the discussion!&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 07 Nov 2015 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>/posts/2015/11/compassion.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/posts/2015/11/compassion.html</guid>
        
        <category>knitr</category>
        
        <category>servr</category>
        
        <category>httpuv</category>
        
        <category>websocket</category>
        
        
        <category>jekyll</category>
        
        <category>rstats</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Silence</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/img/silence.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;fullwidth&quot; src=&quot;/img/moon2.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;marginnote&quot;&gt;Image from the book &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/exec/obidos/ASIN/1907704027&quot;&gt;A Graphic Cosmogony&lt;/a&gt;, Alex Spiro editor.&lt;/span&gt;
About a month ago I had laryngeal surgery and was on strict voice rest for two weeks. This was a new experience. I’ve been on silent retreats but that experience was different. During silent retreats everyone is practicing silence and the environment is very constrained–we meditate, do work practice, study, and eat all in silence at a retreat center. With this experience I was out and about in everyday life. I was teaching my university classes without speaking. I would type out the few things I wanted to say and display them using a projector. If a student asked a question, I would answer in the same way. I was amazed at all the ideas students had when allowed to express themselves without interruption or comment. In one night, I found and read a book on the web, “&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.difficultdialoguesuaa.org/images/uploads/Stop_talking_final.pdf&quot;&gt;Stop Talking: Indigenous Ways of Teaching and Learning and Difficult Dialogues in Higher Education&lt;/a&gt;.” The authors talk about teaching at an ‘earth-based pace’ and advise:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Stop Talking&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Set down your electronic devices.
Set down your books and your pens.
Go outside if possible; otherwise, find a window.
And then for a minute or two, let go of your thoughts
and listen to the wind. Pay attention to the land you
are standing on and to the living things that share
your space. Breathe intentionally from the
common air. Notice how you feel.
Stay with it as long as possible.
Return to it as often as necessary&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During my two weeks of silence, when I was out in the woods walking with my wife, Cheryl, and dogs, in addition to listening to the wind, I would listen to Cheryl talk about something that happened at work, or some idea she had and not interrupt her. And listening to her I realized how much I must interrupt her. Initially, I felt frustrated that I couldn’t respond, but with days of practice I grew more comfortable just listening and felt I was really hearing her voice and who she was.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This whole experience made me think about listening and how sometimes–maybe MOST times–people just want to be heard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When someone says something, they don’t want to be interrupted to hear my, official “&lt;em&gt;What does Ron Zacharski think&lt;/em&gt;”, take on what they are saying. For a number of years I was involved in an online Zen book study group. After a person would say something about a life experience, it would be common for someone to offer an opinion or unasked for advice. Perhaps the best response to someone who shares something about their life is quiet acknowledgement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gloria Steinem in her book “&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/My-Life-Road-Gloria-Steinem/dp/0679456201/ref=sr_1_1?s=books&amp;amp;ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1446399808&amp;amp;sr=1-1&amp;amp;keywords=my+life+on+the+road&quot;&gt;My Life on the Road&lt;/a&gt;” writes:&lt;span class=&quot;marginnote&quot;&gt;Many of these quotes are from the wonderful website &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.brainpickings.org/&quot;&gt;brainpickings.org&lt;/a&gt; by Maria Popova, an amazing and talented professional reader.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;One of the simplest paths to deep change is for the less powerful to speak as much as they listen, and for the more powerful to listen as much as they speak.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She writes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;When people ask me why I still have hope and energy after all these years, I always say: Because I travel. Taking to the road—by which I mean letting the road take you—changed who I thought I was. The road is messy in the way that real life is messy. It leads us out of denial and into reality, out of theory and into practice, out of caution and into action, out of statistics and into stories—in short, out of our heads and into our hearts&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;People in the same room understand and empathize with each other in a way that isn’t possible on the page or screen. Gradually, I became the last thing on earth I would ever have imagined: a public speaker and a gatherer of groups. And this brought an even bigger reward: public listening.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She suggests:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Spend some time on the road… in an on-the-road state of mind, not seeking out the familiar but staying open to whatever comes along. It can begin the moment you leave your door.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Like a jazz musician improvising, or a surfer looking for a wave, or a bird riding a current of air, you’ll be rewarded by moments when everything comes together. Listen to the story of strangers meeting in a snowstorm that Judy Collins sings about in “The Blizzard,” or read Alice Walker’s essay “My Father’s Country Is the Poor.” Each starts in a personal place, takes an unpredictable path, and reaches a destination that is both surprising and inevitable — like the road itself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;More reliably than anything else on earth, the road will force you to live in the present.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Be well.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 01 Nov 2015 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>/posts/2015/11/silence.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/posts/2015/11/silence.html</guid>
        
        <category>knitr</category>
        
        <category>servr</category>
        
        <category>httpuv</category>
        
        <category>websocket</category>
        
        
        <category>jekyll</category>
        
        <category>rstats</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>No talking</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/img/silence.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;fullwidth&quot; src=&quot;/img/silence.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;marginnote&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/photomequickbooth/4380100026/in/photolist-7F4a8Y-6Cy2N6-47c9Kz-8B6aCt-6fXMzG-anJKtB-2Dvfxp-5YdMB9-4bm85J-7pKg3x-8UXrVN-6BZG2Y-MedVu-6xT8Fg-2Y3ueA-4UV1nd-7MDWHm-cK498U-59Xs7g-b8Bmfi-5TP48k-erX4u-28Lovq-6gtKAM-79oqCL-MrKqN-cK492m-4ju1W8-6nEbmC-69rHbT-7uGaMj-5prTY-5prTJ-5prSK-8LXhx8-cK49gu-5prSy-6HrLLb-cnat9o-6DBSie-4Bspgt-9cjoQ6-3BT4VZ-4rwRSD-5qp3ix-wmuxQ9-CEk6R-4ujZUv-5cdKCT-786d5a&quot;&gt;This creative commons Flickr image&lt;/a&gt; is from Nicola Jones.&lt;/span&gt;
Last Friday I had some minor laryngeal surgery in Richmond, Virginia. I have some pain. I am on pain meds that make me loopy. The nurse warned my wife that I might be grumpy because of the steroids I am on (and I think I am grumpier). I am off of caffeine, and on a soft food diet (smoothies, scrambled eggs). I am on strict voice rest for what looks like 2 weeks and then partial voice rest for another week. Amid all this I realized something: it is a lot easier to practice Zen when you are feeling well and things are going your way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The day after the surgery I meditated and it was like switching channels on some cable network that only plays fantastical shows. There I am on some tall fortress made of cushions surveying some battlefield and I am a bit worried the fort will topple over. Focus on my breath. Cheryl and I are having some argument about whether we are currently in Costco or in bed sleeping. Focus. There’s some Great Dane that jumps on his owner’s motorbike for a ride. Eeeks. I am awake, trying to meditate, and I am having a slideshow of weirdness. And the next day’s meditation is more of the same.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s also challenging to practice compassion and generosity. When I am sick &lt;strong&gt;I&lt;/strong&gt; want to be the center of the universe and get a tad grumpy when things don’t go my way.  How come Cheryl is going around and around and around the block trying to find a parking place when she should just park so we can  go in to Boyer’s Ice Cream  and get a nice cold shake for my throat. Doesn’t she know I am sick? A student inititiates a chat in GoogleTalk to get some clarification about a programming assignment and I am irritated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are perfect opportunities for practice. Perfect opportunities to touch grumpiness, irritation, racing wild thoughts. To examine them, to accept them (&lt;em&gt;yes, I am grumpy&lt;/em&gt;) and let them go. It’s easy to practice compassion in a nicey nicey world, perhaps sitting on your meditation cushion spreading compassion mentally to people who are challenging to to. It’s quite another to engage in compassion as right action when that person is hollering at you, or, in my case,  simply engaging in compassion when you are not feeling well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last night I read a bit of the Toni Bernhard book &lt;span class=&quot;marginnote&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/How-Wake-Up-Buddhist-Inspired-Navigating/dp/1614290563/ref=sr_1_3?s=pc&amp;amp;ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1443812094&amp;amp;sr=8-3&amp;amp;keywords=toni+bernhard&quot;&gt;How to Wake Up: A Buddhist-Inspired Guide to Navigating Joy and Sorrow&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt; where she says that when you catch yourself ruminating on your struggles try an exercise she calls “Start where you are.” Well, these last few days I have been ruminating on my struggles so maybe this exercise is for me. She suggests reflecting on how everyone’s life is sometimes easy and sometimes hard. About an hour after reading this passage, I received a post from my Zen Teacher, Daiho. In it he said that he fell hard that morning on a training run in the desert. He broke four bones in his hand, the doctor splinted the hand and is considering pins and screws.  That Zen sandwich of me ruminating on my sorrows, Bernhard saying no one gets a pass on sorrow, and hearing of my teacher’s injury was a good reminder.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No one gets a pass on life’s struggles. Don’t believe me? Listen to some country music. Gary Allen Sings:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;Life ain’t always beautiful
Sometimes it’s just plan hard  
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was good to reflect on the fact that everyone struggles and then acknowledge my difficulties— my struggles. And think &lt;em&gt;I start with where I am.&lt;/em&gt;  To at least make an attempt to accept and engage my life as it is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The task for all of us is to live our lives with this world as it is. It is a practical task. Unless we practice, we will live our lives off-balanced, constantly reacting to what is going on around us. Sickness pushes us one way, …. off balanced and in-chaos. With practice you can live a life filled with poise. Someone or something pushes you and you bobble back to balance. Instead of reacting, you are responsive. Instead of reacting by screaming, shopping, or whatever, you gain an ability to respond and not react and your response is friendliness, compassion, and joy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Be well.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 01 Oct 2015 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>/posts/2015/10/sick.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/posts/2015/10/sick.html</guid>
        
        <category>knitr</category>
        
        <category>servr</category>
        
        <category>httpuv</category>
        
        <category>websocket</category>
        
        
        <category>jekyll</category>
        
        <category>rstats</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The Roshi Makes Shitty Coffee</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/img/shittyCoffee2.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;fullwidth&quot; src=&quot;/img/shittyCoffee2.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;marginnote&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/duncan/19318023014/&quot;&gt;Image by Duncan C.&lt;/a&gt; Creative Commons CC-By-NC 2.0&lt;/span&gt;
My friend, Bobby Byrd has this brief poem in his book &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/Otherwise-Life-Ordinary-Bobby-Byrd/dp/1935955756/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1442454590&amp;amp;sr=8-1&amp;amp;keywords=otherwise+my+life+is+ordinary&quot;&gt;Otherwise, My Life is Ordinary&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;h5 id=&quot;koan&quot;&gt;Koan&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The Roshi makes shitty coffee&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Roshi in this poem refers to Rev. Dr. Harvey Daiho Hilbert Roshi and indeed he makes shitty coffee.  Bobby, I, and a host of others would be at some weekend meditation retreat lead by Daiho. It’s afternoon, we are dragging a bit and all we would have  to drink would be some cheap coffee from a container opened months ago made in an old percolator that Daiho turned on at 5am that morning. Ocassionally Bobby or I would dash to Starbucks to bring coffee back for the people who wanted decent coffee.  &lt;span class=&quot;marginnote&quot;&gt;Of course a real coffee connoisseur wouldn’t dream of drinking Starbucks coffee.&lt;/span&gt; 
That’s not the only time I have had a desire for good coffee.
Several times a year I drive 2,000 miles from Virginia to New Mexico and when I need a caffeine fix, I start looking for a Starbucks coffee shop. At home I grind whole beans in a burr grinder and brew the coffee in a hand drip ceramic coffee dripper.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In one of the first teachings of the Buddha he says that desire is the principal cause of dukkha or suffering. This is expressed beautifully in the poem I mentioned in the last post, Hsin Hsin Ming:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The Great Way is not difficult for those who have no preferences. … Make the smallest distinction, however, and heaven and earth are set infinitely apart&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How do I reconcile  coffee snobbery with this core buddhist belief?  Or how do I reconcile &lt;em&gt;any&lt;/em&gt; of my preferences–my preference for green enchiladas at Chopes in La Mesa, for Frozen Custard from Caliches in Las Cruces or Dairy Godmother in Alexandria over any other ice cream? As mentioned in the last post, it’s not the preference that will lead to suffering but the &lt;strong&gt;attachment&lt;/strong&gt; to that preference. Say I need a coffee fix in West Texas and I drive for several hundred miles without encountering a Starbucks and now I feel life sucks, this trip is misery, on and on because of no Starbucks. This attachment to a preference is a big problem. On the other hand, if I need a coffee fix in West Texas, look for a Starbucks for a hundred miles and. not finding one, stop at a truck stop and enjoy their brew, my preference for Starbucks is no big deal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One way of lessening this attachment to preferences is a self-denial practice proposed by the Stoic, Seneca. In this practice you live &lt;em&gt;as if&lt;/em&gt; you do not have what you prefer. In the coffee case, the practice would be to drink shitty coffee. I tried this twice in the last year. Once I bought a 10.5 ounce jar of Nescafe Instant Coffee from Walmart, which made something like 150 cups of coffee. For months, that was the only coffee I drank at home. The next experiment was not as bad–again a Walmart trip, this time for a 30 ounce plastic tub of Folgers Ground Coffee.  These experiments helped me view good coffee as a perk, as something that was special, and not a requirement for a good day. William Irvine, the author of the worthwhile book &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/Guide-Good-Life-Ancient-Stoic-ebook/dp/B0040JHNQG/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1442885397&amp;amp;sr=8-1&amp;amp;keywords=A+Guide+to+the+Good+Life%3A+The+Ancient+Art+of+Stoic+Joy&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;A Guide to the Good Life: The Ancient Art of Stoic Joy&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; says that one benefit of this approach is that the person who does this grows confident that doing without Starbucks is no big deal. Doing without going to their favorite restaurant or being cold when outside is no big deal. We learn we can easily live without our preferences.  This self-denial is very good practice.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 18 Sep 2015 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>/posts/2015/09/shitty-coffee.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/posts/2015/09/shitty-coffee.html</guid>
        
        <category>knitr</category>
        
        <category>servr</category>
        
        <category>httpuv</category>
        
        <category>websocket</category>
        
        
        <category>jekyll</category>
        
        <category>rstats</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The astronaut and the monk</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/img/astromonk.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;fullwidth&quot; src=&quot;/img/astromonk.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;marginnote&quot;&gt;Both images are in the public domain&lt;/span&gt;
Chris Hadfield is a Canadian astronaut and pehaps  one of the more famous astronauts due to his YouTube videos on a range of topics and his playing guitar&lt;span class=&quot;marginnote&quot;&gt;Check out &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=KaOC9danxNo&quot;&gt;his epic cover of Space Oddity&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;  in space. A few years back I listened to an interview he had with Terry Gross. In it he said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;If the only thing you really enjoyed was whipping around Earth in a spaceship, you’d hate being an astronaut. You can’t view training solely as a stepping stone to something loftier. It’s got to be an end in itself. You train for years. If you viewed training as a dreary chore, not only would you be unhappy every day, but your sense of self-worth and professional purpose would be shattered if you were scrubbed from a mission — or never got one.  Because I didn’t hang my happiness on space flight, I was excited to go to work every single day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He says getting in space depends on many variables and circumstances that are entirely beyond an individual astronaut’s control. So for Hadfield, it always made sense to view space flight “as a bonus, not an entitlement.”” And like any bonus it would be foolhardy to bank on it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This interview reminded me of a poem, Hsin Hsin Ming, written by Sengcan in 6th century China. It starts:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The Great Way is not difficult for those who have no preferences. When love and hate are both absent everything becomes clear and undisguised. Make the smallest distinction, however, and heaven and earth are set infinitely apart.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I keep coming back to this line again and again. My interpretation is more along the lines of &lt;em&gt;The Great Way is not difficult for those who have no ATTACHMENT to preferences.&lt;/em&gt; Of course, we all have preferences–both big and small preferences. Many, many preferences. Maybe we think this current week sucks and this coming weekend looks no better, but the weekend after that, boy oh boy, we plan to head to the mountains, get a room at our favorite hotel, eat at our favorite restaurant. We have it all planned in our minds. But that weekend may not happen as planned. We may end up having to work, or we may get there and find the restaurant is closed for that week, or the town is jammed with a huge loud motorcycle rally. If we were attached to the weekend as planned we could get depressed, angry, you name it. &lt;em&gt;“My weekend is ruined because my favorite restaurant is closed. This whole trip is a bust.”&lt;/em&gt; Believe me, I’ve had similar experiences over even trivial things more times than I care to admit. Some of us are unhappy in our day-to-day lives and view happiness as something that will happen when we attain our goals–a better job, an ideal relationship, a degree. Then we will be happy. But attaining any of these is beyond our complete control and even if we attain some of them, the reality of them might not match our expectations. What a bummer, to put it mildly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Life is more enjoyable, moment by moment, if we are not attached to preferences. If, as Hadfield says, we view our preferences as bonuses and not entitlements. 
Hadfield says. “Too many variables are out of my control. There’s really just one thing I can control: my attitude during the journey.”
Looking back at his life as an astronaut, Hadfield says his job was not about flying around in space: “It was really about making the most of my time here on Earth.” Or to generalize — life isn’t about reaching a set of goals, it is about making the most of our time here on earth.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 09 Sep 2015 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>/posts/2015/09/astronaut.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/posts/2015/09/astronaut.html</guid>
        
        <category>knitr</category>
        
        <category>servr</category>
        
        <category>httpuv</category>
        
        <category>websocket</category>
        
        
        <category>jekyll</category>
        
        <category>rstats</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Hillerman Country</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/img/shiprock2.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;fullwidth&quot; src=&quot;/img/shiprock2.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
Even before moving to New Mexico, I loved Tony Hillerman novels. There I was on a farm in Northern Wisconsin in January–below zero,  snow on the ground– reading Hillerman’s descriptions of Shiprock, Window Rock, Gallup and the terrain and open sky of the Southwest. Now the mystery series has been continued by his daughter, Anne, and I just finished reading her first novel, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/Spider-Womans-Daughter-Leaphorn-Novel/dp/0062270494/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1441487703&amp;amp;sr=8-1&amp;amp;keywords=spider+womans+daughter&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Spider Woman’s Daughter&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. One of the main characters is Officer Bernie Manuelito who worries about a mother who is old and frail, a sister who is drinking heavily (and to Bernie’s eyes wasting her life), an uncle who has been shot in the head and in a coma in Santa Fe, and the investigation of that shooting which seems to be going nowhere.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This morning I thought, &lt;em&gt;Good grief, What a life she has!&lt;/em&gt;  Where is there room for joy and happiness? Then I thought we all have similar lives filled with worry and stress. Worrying about the health of our parents, our own health, the well-being of our children. Stressing over our job, money, our relationships. We have an over-abundance of things to worry and stress about that can keep us occupied 24/7. And this worry acts as a filter to the present moment. We think about our worries instead of clearly seeing what is in front of us. We might be out walking our dog but our minds are regurgitating the latest hassles at work which fill us with a slight anger. We might be sitting with our parents in their living room but our minds are off weaving a story of how frail they look which fills us with worry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the Hillerman novel was focused on just recounting the internal worries of Bernie Manuelito it would be a pretty boring read. Instead, Bernie often stops the internal yakking to appreciate where she is. At times she is present in the moment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Finally, the view she loved, the San Juan River south of the highway, flowing between rows of towering ancient cottonwoods.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The sky was majestic. The Sandia Mountains rose like a rugged blue monolith to the east, glowing in the reflected oranges, vivid reds, and brilliant sunflower hues of the sunset. He put his arm around her as they watched the light change from magenta to smoky rose and dissolve into the soft gray of summer predarkness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We too can work toward being present in the moment. We can be present with our parents in their living room without some distracting constant dialog in our minds. We can walk the dog and simply be walking our dog. Instead of thinking &lt;em&gt;Good grief, my life is so hard. I work long hours, I’m exhausted when I get home. blah, blah, blah.&lt;/em&gt; we can just be present in the moment. That’s where happiness lies. Our lives may indeed be hard. We may work long hours. We may have some illness. But by constantly thinking about all this we are just working ourselves up more and more. More anger, more worry, more suffering. The path out of this is working on being present in the moment. This is the focus of Zen and why we practice meditation.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 02 Sep 2015 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>/posts/2015/09/Hillerman.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/posts/2015/09/Hillerman.html</guid>
        
        <category>knitr</category>
        
        <category>servr</category>
        
        <category>httpuv</category>
        
        <category>websocket</category>
        
        
        <category>jekyll</category>
        
        <category>rstats</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
